Once there was a star.
كانت هناك ذات مرة نجمة.
Like everything else, she was born;
مثل كل شيء آخر، وُلِدت؛
grew to be around 30 times the mass of our sun
فنَمَت لتكون حوالي 30 مرة كتلة شمسنا،
and lived for a very long time.
وعاشت لفترة طويلة جدا.
Exactly how long,
كم من الوقت بالضبط؟
people cannot really tell.
لا يستطيع الناس معرفة ذلك حقا.
Just like everything in life,
تماما مثل كل شيء في الحياة،
she reached the end of her regular star days
فلقد وصلت إلى نهاية أيامها النجمية العادية
when her heart, the core of her life,
عندما قام قلبها، جوهر حياتها،
exhausted its fuel.
باستنفاذ وقودها.
But that was no end.
ولكن تلك لم تكن النهاية.
She transformed into a supernova, and in the process
لقد تحولت إلى سوبر نوفا، وخلال تلك العملية
releasing a tremendous amount of energy,
أطلقت كمية هائلة من الطاقة،
outshining the rest of the galaxy
متألقة على بقية المجرة
and emitting, in one second,
وباعثة ، خلال ثانية واحدة،
the same amount of energy our sun will release in 10 days.
نفس الكمية من الطاقة التي تطلقها شمسنا في 10 أيام.
And she evolved into another role in our galaxy.
ولقد تطورت إلى دور آخر في مجرتنا.
Supernova explosions are very extreme.
إن انفجارات السوبرنوفا متطرفة جدا.
But the ones that emit gamma rays are even more extreme.
ولكن تلك التي تنبعث منها أشعة غاما هي أكثر تطرفا.
In the process of becoming a supernova,
في طريقها إلى أن تصبح سوبر نوفا،
the interior of the star collapses under its own weight
تنهار النجمة من الداخل تحت تأثير وزنها
and it starts rotating ever faster,
وتبدأ في الدوران بشكل سريع ،
like an ice skater when pulling their arms in close to their body.
مثل متزلج الجليد عندما يسحب أيديه بالقرب من جسمه.
In that way, it starts rotating very fast and it increases, powerfully,
وبتلك الطريقة، تبدأ في الدوران بشكل سريع جدا، ويزداد، بقوة،
its magnetic field.
مجالها المغناطيسي.
The matter around the star is dragged around,
يتم سحب المادة الموجودة حول النجم،
and some energy from that rotation is transferred to that matter
ويتم نقل بعض الطاقة الناتجة عن ذلك الدوران إلى المادة
and the magnetic field is increased even further.
ويزداد المجال المغناطيسي أكثر.
In that way, our star had extra energy to outshine the rest of the galaxy
وبهذه الطريقة، كان لدى نجمنا طاقة إضافية ليتفوق على باقي المجرة
in brightness and gamma ray emission.
في السطوع وانبعاث أشعة غاما.
My star, the one in my story,
نجمي، ذلك الموجود في قصتي،
became what is known as a magnetar.
أصبح يعرف بالنجم المغناطيسي.
And just for your information,
ولمعلوماتكم فقط،
the magnetic field of a magnetar is 1,000 trillion times
المجال المغناطيسي لنجم مغناطيسي هو 1000 تريليون مرة
the magnetic field of Earth.
المجال المغناطيسي للأرض.
The most energetic events ever measured by astronomers
أكثر الأحداث نشاطا من أي وقت مضى والتي قاسها علماء الفلك
carry the name gamma-ray bursts
تحمل اسم انفجارات أشعة غاما
because we observe them as bursts most or explosions,
لأننا نشاهدها كاندفاعات نارية غالبا أو انفجارات،
most strongly measured as gamma-ray light.
وتقاس غالبا كأشعة غاما ضوئية.
Our star, like the one in our story that became a magnetar,
نجمنا، مثل ذلك الذي في قصتنا والذي أصبح نجما مغناطيسيا،
is detected as a gamma-ray burst
يتم الكشف عنه كاندفاع لأشعة غاما ضوئية
during the most energetic portion of the explosion.
خلال الجزء الأكثر نشاطا من الانفجار.
Yet, even though gamma-ray bursts are the strongest events
ومع ذلك، فعلى الرغم من أن اندفاعات أشعة غاما هي أقوى الأحداث
ever measured by astronomers,
التي قاسها علماء الفلك لحد الآن،
we cannot see them with our naked eye.
فإنه لا يمكننا رؤيتها بالعين المجردة.
We depend, we rely on other methods
نحن نعتمد على أساليب أخرى
in order to study this gamma-ray light.
من أجل دراسة ضوء أشعة غاما هذا.
We cannot see them with our naked eye.
نحن لا نستطيع أن نراها بالعين المجردة.
We can only see an itty bitty, tiny portion
يمكننا أن نرى فقط قطعة صغيرة جدا، جزءا صغيرا جدا
of the electromagnetic spectrum that we call visible light.
من الطيف الكهرومغناطيسي الذي نسميه الضوء المرئي.
And beyond that, we rely on other methods.
ولأبعد من ذلك، فإننا نعتمد على أساليب أخرى.
Yet as astronomers, we study a wider range of light
ومع ذلك فنحن كعلماء فلك، نقوم بدراسة مجموعة واسعة من الضوء
and we depend on other methods to do that.
ونعتمد على طرق أخرى للقيام بذلك.
On the screen, it may look like this.
على الشاشة، فإن الأمر قد يبدو هكذا.
You're seeing a plot.
أنتم ترون رسما بيانيا.
That is a light curve.
وهو منحنى الضوء.
It's a plot of intensity of light over time.
إنه رسم بياني لشدة الضوء وفق الزمن.
It is a gamma-ray light curve.
وهو منحنى ضوء أشعة غاما.
Sighted astronomers depend on this kind of plot
يعتمد علماء الفلك الذين يمكنهم الإبصار على هذا النوع من التبيانات
in order to interpret how this light intensity changes over time.
لتفسير كيفية تغير كثافة الضوء هذه مع مرور الزمن.
On the left, you will be seeing the light intensity without a burst,
على اليسار، سوف ترون شدة الضوء دون اندفاع،
and on the right, you will be seeing the light intensity with the burst.
وعلى اليمين، سوف ترون شدة الضوء مع الاندفاع (اندفاع اشعة غاما).
Early during my career, I could also see this kind of plot.
في وقت مبكر خلال مسيرتي، كان باستطاعتي أنا أيضا رؤية هذا النوع من الرسوم البيانية.
But then, I lost my sight.
ولكنني بعد مدة، فقدت بصري .
I completely lost my sight because of extended illness,
لقد فقدت بصري تماما بسبب مرض ممتد،
and with it, I lost the opportunity to see this plot
وفقدت معه فرصة رؤية هذا الرسم البياني،
and the opportunity to do my physics.
وفرصة العمل على الفيزياء خاصتي.
It was a very strong transition for me in many ways.
لقد كان هذا تحولا قويا جدا بالنسبة لي في نواح كثيرة.
And professionally, it left me without a way to do my science.
ومهنيا، لم يترك لي أية وسيلة للعمل بعلومي.
I longed to access and scrutinize this energetic light
كنت أتوق للوصول والتدقيق في هذا الضوء النشيط
and figure out the astrophysical cause.
ومعرفة السبب الفيزيائي الفلكي.
I wanted to experience the spacious wonder, the excitement,
أردت تجربة تلك المعجزة الواسعة، تلك الإثارة،
the joy produced by the detection of such a titanic celestial event.
تلك الفرحة الناتجة عن اكتشاف حدث فلكي عملاق كهذا.
I thought long and hard about it,
فكرت طويلا وبجهد في ذلك،
when I suddenly realized that all a light curve is,
وعندها أدركت فجأة أن منحنى الضوء ماهو إلا
is a table of numbers converted into a visual plot.
جدول أعداد ثم تحويله إلى مبيان بصري.
So along with my collaborators,
لذلك قمت جنبا إلى جنب مع شركائي ،
we worked really hard and we translated the numbers into sound.
بالعمل بجد وترجمة الأرقام إلى صوت.
I achieved access to the data,
وحَقَّقْتُ الوصول إلى البيانات،
and today I'm able to do physics at the level of the best astronomer,
واليوم أنا أستطيع القيام بالفيزياء بمستوى أفضل عالم فلك،
using sound.
وذلك باستخدام الصوت.
And what people have been able to do,
وما كان الناس قادرين على القيام به،
mainly visually,
بشكل رئيسي بصريا،
for hundreds of years,
لمئات السنين،
now I do it using sound.
أستطيع أنا الآن القيام به باستخدام الصوت.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Listening to this gamma-ray burst
إن الاستماع إلى انفجار أشعة غاما هذه
that you're seeing on the -- (Applause continues)
التي ترونها على - (تصفيق مستمر)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
Listening to this burst that you're seeing on the screen
إن الاستماع إلى انفجار أشعة غاما هذه التي ترونها على الشاشة
brought something to the ear beyond the obvious burst.
جلب شيئا ما للأذن يفوق الانفجار الظاهر.
Now I'm going to play the burst for you.
سأقوم الآن بتشغيل الانفجار لكم.
It's not music, it's sound.
هذه ليست موسيقى، هذا صوت.
(Digital beeping sounds)
(أصوات تصفير رقمية )
This is scientific data converted into sound,
هذه بيانات علمية تم تحويلها إلى صوت،
and it's mapped in pitch.
وقد تم رسمها بنغمة.
The process is called sonification.
وتسمى هذه العملية بالصوتنة.
So listening to this brought something to the ear
إذن فالاستماع لهذا جلب شيئا ما للأذن
besides the obvious burst.
يفوق الانفجار الظاهر.
When I examine the very strong low-frequency regions,
عندما فحصنا المناطق القوية جدا ذات التردد المنخفض ،
or bass line -- I'm zooming into the bass line now.
أو خط صوت نبرة التردد بيس - أنا أُكبَّر خط صوت نبرة التردد بيس الآن.
We noted resonances characteristic of electrically charged gasses
لاحظنا أصداء مميزة من الغازات المشحونة كهربائيا
like the solar wind.
مثل الرياح الشمسية.
And I want you to hear what I heard.
وأنا أريدكم أن تسمعوا ما سمعْته.
You will hear it as a very fast decrease in volume.
سوف تسمعونها كانخفاض سريع جدا في الصوت.
And because you're sighted, I'm giving you a red line
ولأنكم تبصرون، فسوف أمنحكم خطا أحمرا
indicating what intensity of light is being converted into sound.
يشير إلى شدة الضوء التي يجري تحويلها إلى صوت.
(Digital hum and whistling sound)
(همهمة رقمية وصوت صفير)
The (Whistles) is frogs at home, don't pay attention to that.
إن (الصفير) هو لضفادع في المنزل، لا تهتموا لذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Digital hum and whistling sound)
(همهمة رقمية وصوت الصفير)
I think you heard it, right?
أعتقد أنكم سمعتموها، أليس كذلك؟
So what we found
إذن فما وجدناه هو
is that the bursts last long enough in order to support wave resonances,
أن الانفجارات النارية تستمر لما يكفي من الوقت من أجل دعم أصداء الموجة،
which are things caused by exchanges of energy between particles
وهي أشياء تسببها تبادلات الطاقة بين الجسيمات
that may have been excited,
والتي قد تكون متهيجة،
that depend on the volume.
وتعتمد على الصوت.
You may remember that I said that the matter around the star
لعلكم تتذكرون أنني قلت أنه يتم
is dragged around?
سحب المادة المتواجدة حول النجم ؟
It transmits power with frequency and field distribution
إنها تنقل القوة مع التردد وتوزيع المجال
determined by the dimensions.
الذي تحدده الأبعاد.
You may remember that we were talking about a super-massive star
لعلكم تتذكرون أننا كنا نتحدث عن نجم هائل الحجم
that became a very strong magnetic field magnetar.
والذي أصبح نجما مغناطيسيا ذو مجال مغناطيسي قوي جدا.
If this is the case, then outflows from the exploding star
إذا كان الأمر كذلك، فإن التدفقات الخارجة من النجم المتفجر
may be associated with this gamma-ray burst.
قد تكون مرتبطة بانفجار أشعة غاما هذا.
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذالك؟
That star formation may be a very important part
أن تَكوُّن النجوم قد يكون جزءا مهما جدا
of these supernova explosions.
من انفجارات السوبرنوفا هذه.
Listening to this very gamma-ray burst brought us to the notion
إن الاستماع إلى انفجار أشعة غاما هذه أدى بنا إلى فكرة
that the use of sound as an adjunctive visual display
أن استخدام الصوت باعتباره عرضا مرئيا مساعد
may also support sighted astronomers
قد يدعم أيضا علماء الفلك المبصرين
in the search for more information in the data.
في البحث عن مزيد من المعلومات في البيانات.
Simultaneously, I worked on analyzing measurements from other telescopes,
في الوقت نفسه، عَملتُ على تحليل قياسات من تلسكوبات أخرى،
and my experiments demonstrated
وأظهرت تجاربي
that when you use sound as an adjunctive visual display,
أنه وعند استخدام الصوت كعرض مرئي مساعد،
astronomers can find more information
فإنه وبإمكان الفلكيين العثور على مزيد من المعلومات
in this now more accessible data set.
في مجموعة البيانات هذه التي يمكن الوصول إليها بشكل أفضل الآن.
This ability to transform data into sound
هذه القدرة على تحويل البيانات إلى صوت
gives astronomy a tremendous power of transformation.
تمنح علم الفلك قوة هائلة من التحول.
And the fact that a field that is so visual may be improved
وحقيقة أن مجالا بصريا بشكل كبير يمكن أن يتم تحسينه
in order to include anyone with interest in understanding what lies in the heavens
من أجل أن يشمل أي شخص لديه اهتمام بفهم ما يكمن في السماوات
is a spirit-lifter.
هو أمر محمس.
When I lost my sight,
عندما فقدت بصري،
I noticed that I didn't have access
لاحظت أنني لا أملك إمكانية الوصول
to the same amount and quality of information
إلى نفس كمية ونوعية المعلومات
a sighted astronomer had.
التي كان يملكها الفلكي المبصر.
It was not until we innovated with the sonification process
وبعد إبداعنا في عملية الصوتنة
that I regained the hope to be a productive member of the field
استعدت أمل أن أكون عضوا منتجا في الميدان
that I had worked so hard to be part of.
الذي عملت بجد لأكون جزءا منه.
Yet, information access is not the only area in astronomy
ومع ذلك، فإن الوصول إلى المعلومة ليس المجال الوحيد في علم الفلك
where this is important.
حيث يعتبر هذا مهما.
The situation is systemic
إن الوضع نظامي
and scientific fields are not keeping up.
والمجالات العلمية ليست مواكبة.
The body is something changeable --
إن الجسد هو شيء متغير -
anyone may develop a disability at any point.
يمكن لأي شخص أن يصبح عاجزا في أي لحظة.
Let's think about, for example,
دعونا نفكر، على سبيل المثال،
scientists that are already at the top of their careers.
في العلماء الذين هم بالفعل في أوج وظائفهم.
What happens to them if they develop a disability?
مالذي يحدث لهم إذا ما أصيبوا بإعاقة ما؟
Will they feel excommunicated as I did?
هل سيشعرون بالعزل مثلي؟
Information access empowers us to flourish.
إن الوصول إلى المعلومة يخول لنا الازدهار.
It gives us equal opportunities to display our talents
ويمنحنا فرصا متساوية لعرض مواهبنا
and choose what we want to do with our lives,
واختيار ما نريد أن نفعله في حياتنا،
based on interest and not based on potential barriers.
بناء على الاهتمامات لا الحواجز المحتملة.
When we give people the opportunity to succeed without limits,
عندما نعطي الناس فرصة للنجاح بلا حدود،
that will lead to personal fulfillment and prospering life.
فإن ذلك من شأنه أن يؤدي إلى تحقيق الذات وإلى حياة مزدهرة.
And I think that the use of sound in astronomy
وأنا أعتقد أن استخدام الصوت في علم الفلك
is helping us to achieve that and to contribute to science.
يساعدنا على تحقيق ذلك والمساهمة في العلم.
While other countries told me that the study of perception techniques
في حين أخبرتني بلدان أخرى أن دراسة تقنيات التصور
in order to study astronomy data is not relevant to astronomy
من أجل دراسة بيانات علم الفلك لا صلة لها بالفلك
because there are no blind astronomers in the field,
لأنه لا وجود لعلماء فلك عميان في هذا الميدان،
South Africa said, "We want people with disabilities
قالت لي جنوب أفريقيا: "نحن نريد من أشخاص ذوي إعاقات
to contribute to the field."
المساهمة في هذا الميدان".
Right now, I'm working
الآن، أنا أعمل
at the South African Astronomical Observatory,
في المرصد الفلكي لجنوب أفريقيا،
at the Office of Astronomy for Development.
في مكتب علم الفلك للتنمية.
There, we are working on sonification techniques and analysis methods
نحن نعمل هناك على تقنيات الصوتنة وطرق التحليل
to impact the students of the Athlone School for the Blind.
للتأثير على طلاب مدرسة أثلون للمكفوفين.
These students will be learning radio astronomy,
هؤلاء الطلاب سوف يتعلمون علم الفلك الراديوي،
and they will be learning the sonification methods
وسوف يتعلمون أساليب الصوتنة
in order to study astronomical events like huge ejections of energy
لدراسة الأحداث الفلكية مثل انبعاثات الكتل الضخمة من الطاقة
from the sun, known as coronal mass ejections.
من الشمس، والمعروفة باسم الانبعاث الكتلي الإكليلي.
What we learn with these students --
ما نتعلمه مع هؤلاء الطلاب -
these students have multiple disabilities and coping strategies
هؤلاء الطلاب لديهم إعاقات متعددة واستراتيجيات تغلب
that will be accommodated --
التي سوف يتم استيعابها -
what we learn with these students will directly impact
ما نتعلمه مع هؤلاء الطلاب سوف يؤثر بشكل مباشر
the way things are being done at the professional level.
على الطريقة التي تجري بها الأمور على المستوى المهني.
I humbly call this development.
أنا أدعو هذا بكل تواضع تطورا.
And this is happening right now.
وهذا يحدث الآن.
I think that science is for everyone.
أنا أعتقد أن العلم هو للجميع.
It belongs to the people,
فهو ينتمي إلى الشعب،
and it has to be available to everyone,
وعليه أن يكون متاحا للجميع،
because we are all natural explorers.
لأننا جميعا مستكشفون طبيعيون.
I think that if we limit people with disabilities
أنا أعتقد أنه إذا ما قيدنا الأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة
from participating in science,
من المشاركة في العلم،
we'll sever our links with history and with society.
فسوف نقطع بذلك علاقاتنا مع التاريخ ومع المجتمع.
I dream of a level scientific playing field,
أنا أحلم بميدان علمي متكافئ ،
where people encourage respect and respect each other,
حيث يشجع الناس على الاحترام ويحترمون بعضهم البعض،
where people exchange strategies and discover together.
حيث يتبادل الناس الاستراتيجيات ويكتشفون معا.
If people with disabilities are allowed into the scientific field,
إذا تم السماح للأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة بولوج المجال العلمي،
an explosion, a huge titanic burst of knowledge will take place,
فسيحدث انفجار واندفاع جبار من المعرفة ،
I am sure.
أنا واثقة من هذا.
(Digital beeping sounds)
( أصوات صفير رقمية)
That is the titanic burst.
هذا هو الانفجار الجبار.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)